A Finding Aid to the Jack Lenor Larsen Papers, 1941-2003, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jack Lenor Larsen papers
1941-2003
Archives of American Art
Larsen, Jack Lenor
AAA.larsjack
Archival Resource Key
3.7 Linear feet
The Jack Lenor Larsen papers measure 3.7 linear feet and date from 1941-2003. Larsen was a renowned weaver and designer, entrepreneur, and a scholar who wrote and lectured on modernist design. His career in the New York design world is documented by biographical materials, correspondence, writings by and about him, various printed materials and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records were donated to the Archives in 2004 by Jack Lenor Larsen in connection with the Nanette L. Laitman Documentation Project for Craft and Decorative Arts in America.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Jack Lenor Larsen (b. 1927), based in New York and of international reputation, has been deeply involved in the design of hand woven fabric and its application to modernist interior design. An international entrepreneur, Larsen also has written books on design and has been a frequent lecturer.
Larsen was born in Seattle, Washington to parents of Canadian/Scandinavian descent; his father was a building contractor. Larsen studied architecture at the University of Washington and became interested in materials design, receiving his M.F.A. from Cranbrook Academy of Art in Michigan in 1951. Following graduation, he opened a studio in New York and established Jack Lenor Larsen Incorporated. Just months later, Larsen successfully competed for the commission to design draperies for the important glass walled Lever House building on Park Avenue designed by Skidmore, Owings and Merrill.
Larsen was highly successful in marketing his ideas and innovations, which included combining metallic thread with natural polished linen and hand woven fabrics consisting of varied yarns in random and repeating patterns. This later style of fabric became known as the "Larsen Look" and was synonymous with modern design. Larsen's firm successfully adapted technological advances to fabric design but also used ancient techniques; they were first to design fabrics for jet air planes, stretch upholsestry and printed velvets.
In 1958-1960, Larsen represented the United States Department of State in Vietnam and Taiwan, studying those countries' crafts with the goal of developing industry to create jobs and products for export. Larsen then saw the opportunity for international fabric design and production. He travelled to Latin America, Africa and Asia to study local crafts and weaving with an eye towards business opportunites, focusing on hand spun and hand woven silks. By the 1990s Larsen was producing fabric in over 30 countries. In 1997, Jack Lenor Larsen, Inc. merged with the British fabric house, Cowtan and Tout and became the United States subsidiary of the British company, Colefax and Fowler.
Many museums have collected and/or exhibited Larsen fabrics. Notable among them are The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Musee des Arts Decoratifs (in the Louvre Museum), Museum of Modern Art, Stedelijk Museum in Amsterdam, and the Victoria and Albert Museum in London. In addition, Larsen is the author of several books relating to fabric and fabric design including Material Wealth: Living with Luxurious Fabrics (an international survey of contemporary fabric design) and an autobiography, Jack Lenor Larsen: A Weaver's Memoir.
Scope and Content Note
The Jack Lenor Larsen papers measure 3.7 linear feet and date from 1941-2003. Larson was a renowned weaver and designer, entrepreneur, and a scholar who wrote and lectured on modernist design. His career in the New York design world is documented by biographical materials, correspondence, writings by and about him, various printed materials and photographs.
Found are biographical materials and artifacts including items from his early years, 4 volumes of daily planners and numerous awards. Correspondence includes letters from notables such as Isamu Noguchi, Walter F. Mondale, and various craft artists such as Helen W. Drutt English, Magdalena Abakanowicz, and Beatrice Wood, and author Hannah Tillich, widow of Paul Tillich. Business correspondence is from museums, professional societies, magazines and other organizations such as the Josef Albers Foundation. Larsen also curated textile exhibitions and there are records pertaining to these exhibitions.
There are a substantial number of writings, lectures and speeches by Larsen, and proofs of a book he co-authored with Mildred Constantin, Beyond Craft: The Art of Fabric. Also found are writings about Larsen and 3 interviews with him including a 1965 videotaped interview, 2 transcribed interviews, and an audio tape of Larsen's talk "Personal Perspective," presented at a conference of the American Craft Council.
Photographs show Larsen and his employees at work and at professional events. Photographs removed from albums retain their original order. Lastly, there are printed materials include catalogs and announcements, newspaper and magazine clippings, and press and promotional materials.
Arrangement
The Jack Lenor Larsen papers are organized into 7 series based primarily on record type and arranged chronologically.
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1941-2001, (Box 1, 5; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1958-2003, (Box 1; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Exhibition Records, 1986-1990, (Boxes 1-2; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings, 1950-2003, (Boxes 2-3; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographs, 1970-1992, (Box 3, 5; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1972-2002, (Boxes 4-5; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Audio Recordings, 1965, (Box 4; 0.1 linear feet)
Audiocassettes; Weavers -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Sound recordings; Interviews; Modernism (Art); Video recordings; Textile design; Josef Albers Foundation; Noguchi, Isamu, 1904-1988; Constantine, Mildred; Drutt, Helen Williams; Tillich, Hanna; Wood, Beatrice; Mondale, Walter F., 1928-; Abakanowicz, Magdalena
- Biographical Material, 1941-2001; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 1, 5
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material consists mostly of diplomas, honorary doctorates, and awards and certificates from associations, institutions and colleges. There are 4 volumes of daily planners, an address book, Boy Scout merit badges and sash, and a short genealogical outline.
  - Family Tree, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Passports, 1955-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Diplomas, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Bremerton High School, 1945; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - University of Washington, 1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Honorary Doctorates, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Parsons School of Design, 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Oversized material housed in Box 5
    - Philadelphia College of Art, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Awards and Certificates, (College of Arts and Sciences, University of Washington), 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Washington Intermediate School Pupil's Quarterly Report, 1941-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Eagle Scout Badge, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Boy Scout Merit Badges and Sash, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Elmer Lenor Larsen Memorial, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Daily Planners and Address Book, 1991-2001; Archival Resource Key; 4 Volumes (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Honorary Doctorate, (Parsons School of Design), 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Certificates, Archival Resource Key (Box 5)
    - American Institute of Decorators, 1954-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - American Society of Interior Designers, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Deco Press, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - House and Garden, 1958; 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Industrial Design Review, 1969-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Institute of Business Designers, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - International Contract Product Design Award, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - The Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1925; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Mostra Internazionale dell' Arredamento, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Paulex, Inc., 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Printing Industries of Metropolitan New York, Inc., 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Resources Council Product Design Awards Programs, 1974-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - The Royal Society for the Encouragement of Arts, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Surface Design Association, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Upholstery Leather Group, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1958-2003; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1
  This series contains personal and professional correspondence including letters from craft artists and other notables such as Walter F. Mondale, Isamu Noguchi, and Hannah Tillich, (Mrs. Paul Tillich). Also found are greeting cards and postcards from colleagues, friends and family including some artwork as illustrations or enclosures. Professional correspondence includes letters from museums and art institutions, including the American Craft Museum, the Corning Museum of Glass, and the Josef Albers Foundation, design and manufacturing corporations and magazines such as Connoisseur and Contact.
  - Personal Correspondence, 1958; 1972-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1998-2003; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Business Correspondence, 1981-2003; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters, Invitations, Party/Event Lists, undated; 1991-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Exhibition Records, 1986-1990; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  This series is comprised of records of exhibitions at the Bellas Artes Gallery in Santa Fe, New Mexico and the Erie Art Museum in Erie, Pennsylvania, both curated by Larsen. Also found is correspondence, other business documentation, slides and printed material.
  - Bellas Artes Gallery, Archival Resource Key
    - Correspondence, undated; 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Artists, 1988-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Printed Material, 1988-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Slides, 1989; Archival Resource Key; (35mm color) (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Erie Art Museum, Archival Resource Key
    - Biographies, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, Artists, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Erie Art Museum, Archival Resource Key
    - Correspondence, Artists, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General Correspondence, 1986-1988; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Artist Lists, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Shipping Expense, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Photographs, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Slides of Artwork, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
- Writings, 1950-2003; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 1.3 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Writings by Larsen include a foreword to The Miracle of Ancient at the Peru Merrin Gallery and many lectures, speeches and magazine articles. Larsen lectured at prestigious institutions including the Louvre Museum, The Metropolitan Museum of Art, Rhode Island School of Design, and World Craft Council. Also found are a draft of an unpublished book and articles by Larsen for publications such as American Craft, Art and Antiques and Fiber Arts, I.D. There also are writings about Larsen such as "Body and Soul: Jack Lenor Larsen as Designer and Collector" by David Revere McFadden, Chief Curator at the Museum of Art and Design.
  Arrangement note
  The materials in the folders titled Lectures and Writings by Larsen preserve their original order.
  - Writings by Larsen, 1983-1988; undated; 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Foreword for The Miracle of Ancient Peru at the Merrin Galley together with correspondence, contracts and printed material, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Writings about Larsen, undated; 1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lectures and Speeches by Larsen, 1997; undated; 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Lectures and Speeches about Larsen, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lecture Notes by Larsen, 1964-2002; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
  - Master List of Lectures and Writings by Larsen, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lectures and Writings by Larsen 1-80, undated; 1970-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19-24)
  - Lectures and Writings by Larsen 81-189, 1987-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
  - Transcript of Larsen Interview by Susan Lindsay, 1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Transcript of Larsen Interview by Suzanne Ramljak, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Photographs, circa 1970-1992; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3, 5
  This series includes photographs of Larsen and his employees at work and professional activities. The photographs have been removed from their albums, retaining their original order.
  - Photograph Albums 1-2, 4, undated; circa 1970-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Photograph Album 3, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Photograph Album 5, RHIDEC Los Angeles, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Trade Shows, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Events, MK 40th Anniversary, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Photographs of Fabrics designed by Marga Hielle-Vatter, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Printed Material, 1972-2002; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  Printed material includes announcements, magazine and newspaper clippings, catalogues and journals. Also found are press materials for Larsen's "Terra Nova" Collection, designed in collaboration with Museum Industries and the Museum of the American Indian and a proof of Beyond Craft: The Art Fabric, a book co-written by Mildred Constantine and Jack Lenor Larsen.
  - Announcements, 1992-2002; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1972-1996; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Catalogs and Journals, 1986-1992; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Press Materials, "Terra Nova,", 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Poster, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Programs, 1992-1996; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Proofs, Beyond Craft: The Art Fabric, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Audio Recordings, 1965; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 4
  This series consists of a radio interview with Larsen aired on KCBS, San Francisco and a talk titled "Personal Perspective" that Larsen presented at a meeting of the American Craft Council.
  - Radio Interview, KCBS, San Francisco, Jack Lenor Larsen and Helen Bentley, 1965; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound tape reel (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Personal Perspective," talk by Jack Lenor Larsen, undated; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassette (Box 4, Folder 8)